[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE radio is brought to you by the ITE
computer society and by it e software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[Music]
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my
guest is Daniel Stenberg. Daniel is a
Swedish internet protocol expert and
developer who has participated in and
worked with open-source software for 30
years. He is most known for being the
founder and lead developer of the curl
project, one of the world's most widely
used software components. He also
participates in protocol development
within the IETF and has authored books
on curl, open-source, HTTP version two
and three and more. Requent public
speaker, Daniel is employed by Wolf SSL.
Daniel, welcome back to Software
Engineering Radio. Is there anything I
missed in your bio that you'd like to
add?
>> I don't think so. I think that covers
pretty much what I do.
>> Yeah, it's always very impressive
reading that out for you. I like it.
>> Thank you.
>> So, today our show is called Daniel
Stenberg on removing rust from curl. So,
what I want the listeners to get out
from this hopefully is to understand why
you wanted to bring rust into the
project. how you brought rust into the
curl project to understand why you I'm
going to use the word aband in the
attempt but decided not to do it. Same
same and what the future holds and then
hopefully help everyone understand the
lessons learned so if someone else
attempts or if you come back to it we're
all much wiser for the process. So let's
lay some foundation and remind our
listeners what curl is. I think you're
probably the best person to answer that
Daniel.
>> I'm not sure I'm the best one. I I
struggle sometimes to explain it but I
guess it depends on well what you know
and what you understand about things but
curl is a command line tool and a
library for doing network transfers
really internet transfers using URLs so
it's most widely known then for doing
HTTP and HTTPS but it supports 28
different URL schemes so including email
protocols IMAP SMTP 3 and FTP and SFTP
and SCP P. So it has a lot of transfer
protocols and I could also just
continue. So the command line tool is
often what developers think about when I
say curl. But of course lib curl is the
most widely used component which is
that's the library that is embedded and
used by millions and billions of devices
that are then doing internet transfers
using lib curl. So one very important
key factor with curl is stability,
security and in particular then AI and
API stability that we provide solid and
stable way to use it basically forever
so that all our users in the world can
just upgrade to the latest curl without
having the pain of adjusting things in
the AI or API.
>> It takes a lot of effort, a lot of
testing, a lot of work.
>> It does indeed. You said it's used in
billions of devices. Do you have a top
five list of where you know it's used
just to help listeners
>> by volume? I think nothing compares to
the mobile phones and tablets. So it's
an embedded component in iOS and in
Android. So it's basically on every
smartphone and every tablet that exists
and that's what 7 billion devices or
something.
>> Yeah. I was going to ask how many users
does it have but that answers that
question.
>> Yeah. So basically I tend to avoid the
word users then because it's a little
bit weird since it's a library. So it's
getting used by others. So it's not
really users but embedded in different
tools and applications. And the fun part
about it being used in all these mobile
phones is also that lib curl is a
library right used embedded in these
mobile phone operating systems but they
don't expose the API to applications. So
a lot of apps ship and bundle their own
copy of lib curl. So typical phone today
you have multiple installations of curl
actually because a lot of high volume
apps also ship it and bundle it because
they want to use it but they can't
access it from the OS level. So in a
typical phone with a lot of apps you
have maybe five or 10 installations of
curl.
>> Oh wow. Yeah. I was going to mention
that I just bought the Nintendo Switch 2
and someone listed curl in the credits
to that as well. So obviously Nintendo
use it.
>> All game consoles have it embedded as
well.
>> And do you get support from those guys
in any shape or form? Android, Apple,
Google, Nintendo. Are you not allowed to
say?
>> The standard answer is no, I don't. So I
have a few customers. Is actually a few.
So it's far too few than I would prefer.
So most users like these big ones,
they're just using the open source
version for free and seem to be happy
with that. I try to get as many as
possible to actually pay for support and
help them use curl properly so that they
can sponsor me for my maintenance and
ongoing work. And not only me, of
course, the rest of the team as well,
but it's a hard sell sometimes.
>> And how many in the team do you have
full-time or volunteer?
>> I'm the only one that is full-time, so
it's a small team. It just blows my mind
when people actually explain, you know,
critical software, critical internet
software like this and it's just a
person or a couple of people. Nobody
really understands that, do they? Unless
they're in the open source world. That's
true. And also, it sort of just suffers
a little bit from the classical economic
terms that if they don't have to pay,
they prefer not to pay. So all of these
companies, they they don't have to pay.
So they mostly just don't. Even though
maybe morally or something they should
or could but they will.
>> Yeah, I think they assume that someone
is and that's nobody actually asked that
question. I don't know. Okay. So, I
reached out to you because I read a blog
post December last year, so 6 months ago
or so, called dropping hyper. Now, cuz
I'm in the Rust world and I've done
quite a few shows on Rust, I know what
hyper is. Could you tell me what hyper
is before I move on to the next stage?
Yeah. So, Hyper is well close to the lib
curl alternative in the Rust world. It
is a HTTP and HTTPS library for Rust.
Well, I think that pretty much sums it
up. So, it's an API to do HTTP in
different ways.
>> So, the background here is I'll
summarize of what I understand, but you
can correct me obviously. So
historically there is or was memory
related issues and bugs that come up and
the driving force was to bring a memory
safe language or version of the HTTP
library in to curl. Is that correct or
>> Yeah, exactly. Curl is written in C,
right? It's from the '9s. So it's one of
these old classical styles of open
source projects. So it's written in C.
is unsafe and we certainly have our
share of memory related security issues
over time and curl also has this backend
system which means that when you build
curl you pretty much decide which
backends you want and all those backends
are powered by different third party
libraries. So for example, if you want
TLS support, that TLS is provided by an
external library that someone else wrote
that with an interface and typically
with an allow difference. You can select
which TLS library you want to support
and so on. And we have different back
ends for SSH and content encoding and
different parts IDN and name resolving
so on. So it is sort of in the nature
already that curl offers a selection of
different backends when you build it. So
the idea was then so curl is written in
C maybe we should try to make the final
build use more memory safe code and by
memory safe than being using libraries
written for example in rust. Rust is
probably the most suitable replacement
when it comes to this. So this was
actually then a sponsored thing from
ISRG in their Proximo project. ISRJ
being the team behind let's encrypt
right and they have this ongoing project
to replace memory unsafe projects with
safe projects pretty much rewriting
things from unsafe languages into Rust.
So they sponsored this. So the idea was
then that we would introduce a new HTTP
back end in curl that would be powered
by hyper the Rust library. So by
building curl with this HTTP back end,
we would get a build that would then use
more memory safe code than we would
otherwise have. But it was then an
optional build, right? So you could
either use the native C version or use
the hyper powered version.
>> Yeah. So just to summarize, you've got
the curl project that can offer 28
different protocols depending on what
you configure when you're compiling it
or what's available on the operating
system or the build environment. Those
protocols will then have a back end. So
say you did well, we're talking about
HTTP. So HTTP we could opt to use the
original one in curl and C or another
one if there's one there. And the same
for like TLS, you could use different
libraries to provide that protocol
capability. Exactly.
>> Because traditionally you've had a lot
of memory safety issues. Rust was the
current offering today that would make
sense to bring in and obviously a
rewrite in Rust as the as the term is or
rewriting anything would just be insane.
So doing it bit by bit like this is the
exactly it's pretty much the only viable
way forward to introduce more memory
safety that it is to use more and more
alternative backends and backends
written in memory safe languages. So
that was sort of the idea that we would
then do it this way or we did it too. So
it was more than an idea. It was
actually also made a reality.
>> And how did you decide was hyper like
the number one rust offering or did you
have some criteria? Could you give us
some examples around that thought
process?
>> Oh, it was actually not that much of a
thought process because well I'm not
that much into the Rust ecosystem and
the Rust world really. So I actually
went pretty much with the suggestions
from the ISRG people. So Josh and the
guys there and I talked to Sean
MacArthur who's the lead maintainer of
Hyper. So it was actually a pretty quick
process that we deemed it seemed like a
suitable library to use and at the
appropriate level sort of the
abstraction level in the stack. So we
deemed it a suitable thing to build on
and with.
>> Okay. So you had guidance. What does
that stand for? internet something ISR
>> Internet Security Research Group. I
think it's something you more or less
nonsensical. Well, it's they they let's
encrypt that's what they did.
>> Yeah,
>> they created I think it's a foundation
or something. It's a nonprofit something
isrg.
>> Cool. And they sort of gave guidance on
that and
>> Exactly. And they sponsored this work,
right? So, we sort of back and forth a
bit on exactly their idea and my idea
and how we could make that a reality.
And then I talked a lot with Sean as
well. And Sean's the maintainer of or
the
>> hyper. Yeah, hyper.
>> Yeah, exactly. Because when I started
this, so curl is written in C, right?
And hyper is written in Rust. And while
there is a way, and this was years ago
we started this. So I needed a way then
to interface Hyper using C. So I needed
a glue layer to make sure that we could
use Hyper properly from C. And that
didn't exist back then in Hyper. So I
had a lot of back and forth with Sean
about that and creating that while doing
this work in curl. So it was a lot of we
had to do the work in several different
places actually.
>> Yeah. So it wasn't just here's a Rust
library that has a form function
interface ready for C to use on the
shelf and you just grabbed it. There was
a lot more to it.
>> Exactly. It was pretty early work in
doing this. So there was a lot of moving
pieces actually that had to be done to
make it work.
>> Yeah. And the FFI sort of landscape has
improved quite a lot in the past 5
years, hasn't it? Cuz I'm using it
myself in another project.
>> Yes, exactly. It has certainly improved
since we're also using I mean since I
mentioned all these different backends,
you can still build curl with other rust
back ends. So we support rustles for
example the TLS version from Rust and we
support key which is a HTP3 and quick
library that's also written in Rust. So
there's still ways to build curl with
Rust powered backends. So I'm still
slight and touching the word that world
still.
>> Oh, so it's just hyper that you removed
which provides the
>> Exactly. So we didn't actually remove
all the ways to do Rust. We removed
Hyper and Hyper was actually the only
HTTP back end. The other ones I
mentioned now are TLS backend. It's a TS
back end and an HTTP3 back end. So
different places they glue in into the
stack.
>> So Hyper was HTTP2.
>> HTTP one and two.
>> Oh, one and two. Yeah, forget about one.
And because it was funded by them and
they gave you guidance helped not have
to make a lot of decisions with what
you're picking. So you didn't have to
start protocol parcel from scratch in
Rust.
>> Exactly. Because that was really never a
good idea. So because that's quite a lot
of work and I'm not really a Rust guy
myself. So I wouldn't be a suitable
person to write it in Rust anyway. And
by using something that was already
there, proven working and everything, it
was I would say it's what is pretty
suitable option to go with.
>> Yeah, cuz as I understand it, when
you're talking about bringing Rust in or
rewriting Rust or porting to Rust, the
options would be what you've done. You
bring in something established or you
port the C code. You look at the C code
on one screen and on the other screen
you're rewriting that C rust which it
does work and it kind of doesn't.
There's the rust a dramatic way which
I've done a show on that by the way.
Most of my year has been spent on rust
stuff. So I'll just list a couple of
shows for the listeners. The latest one
was show 672 on rust in production with
Luca 670 with Matias on prototyping in
Rust which was really enjoyable. And
then we did show 659 on idiomatic Rust.
So there are some other ones for people
to listen to. Anyway, so creating it
from scratch or porting your C code to a
Rust equivalent was just insane. And
just to close off this section before we
move on to the actual process of what
you did, how do you see most of the
memory related issues in curl? Is it in
your implementation of the HTTP spec or
is it just spread across different
backends and different integrations?
Where do you see the most pain? That's a
really good question. I actually don't
think I've had them mostly in the HTTP
related parsing code. So it wasn't
really addressing where I think I had
the most. But it's really hard to find
that pattern, right? Where do we do the
most mistakes and how do we fix them? So
typically when we get security problems,
we of course try to see the pattern and
see what we can learn from that and what
we can do to avoid them in the future
and so on. But they tend to be spread
out in different ways. But also we have
al over the last I would say maybe even
10 years we have done several different
things internally in curl sort of to
make it harder to do those mistakes we
sometimes did in the past. So I also
think that there are many ways that we
can actually just write better C to
avoid some of those mistakes. So there
are many different things that are
happening at the same time. So at the
same time we tried to maybe introduce
more Rust code. We also made sure that
we did better C code and avoided some
things that obviously things that were a
little too easy for us to do wrong and
insert mistakes with. So nowadays we
sort of introduce more internal helper
functions and rules on how to do things
just to avoid the risk of mistakes more.
>> Yeah. Trying to centralize where you do
some of the risky things.
>> Exactly. For example, like that. Yes. I
follow your blog and whenever you're
doing stuff on LinkedIn or what have you
and I think there was a bug that was
like 20 years old or something, wasn't
there that came out of nowhere because
it was some obscure usage. So there's
always stuff lying around.
>> Yes. Yes. Security is really hard.
>> Yes. And saw your post about I'll put
this in the show notes about all the new
AI stuff coming through reporting
security memory issues. That's all just
made well it doesn't make sense. the
stuff that is getting submitted
>> doesn't relate to the code.
>> Yeah.
>> But on the flip side, maybe there's
something there that can do some
analysis to try and find some type of
correlation. But I think we've kind of
lost the trust on some of that at the
moment. So there's a bit of work to be
done there.
>> Oh yes. Yeah. Of course, the dream is
that these tools should be able to find
problems because in theory they should,
but I think we have more work to do
before they can do that reliably. Yeah,
I always imagine them just kind of
walking through your code, running some
tests, generating fuzz tests, doing all
the stuff that we all hear every day,
and then it just gives you a nice little
summary report saying, "Oh, by the way,
we just did this weird thing and found
this." You're like, "Oh, thanks." But
yeah, I don't know, a wee bit away from
that.
>> Yes.
>> So, let's move on then. So, just to
close that off, Hyper is the sort of
most popular established, not the only
one, but the one that you were advised
to play with. You didn't start from
scratch cuz that would be insane. And
this part of bringing Rust in wasn't
trying to solve the most or a really
common memory related issue. It's just
something that was the right way to
start.
>> Exactly. And the idea was then so I mean
since we already had this concept of
different backends, this would be one
more way to just bring in another
backend and then replacing native code
and we could then in theory introduce
even more backends in the future, right?
replace more parts of curl by creating
new backends that would be written in
Rust. So in theory that could over time
be more or less that rewrite to Rust
that I wouldn't do but it would be
another way to do it by just replacing
component by component over a long
period of time. So is this the only bit
of Rust that So we've got the backends
that implement the protocol that you're
providing because this has been pulled
out. Is it only the curl implementation
that's left or is there other one?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> So basically I created this HTTP the
notion of an HTTP back end. It didn't
exist before this. So I created it on
the behalf of being so that I could use
hyper for it hyper or native. And then
when I removed the hyper approach there
was no other backend. So I b pretty much
closed that door and now we don't have
any HTTP back end anymore. We just have
the native code for it. Yeah, I think I
read the removal history in your get
repo where you closed all the options.
>> I also think part of the lesson by the
whole hyper journey and adventure part
of the lesson there is how we should do
such an HTTP back end the next time we
try it. So I think it was a little bit
weirdly done and I think that's also one
reason sort of why I removed it
completely instead of leaving it open
for a potential future. So it wasn't
really done the best way and we have
since remodeled internals and actually
improved a lot of things refactoring the
internals of curl and lib curl. So I
think the next time we try to do an HTTP
back end we're in a much better position
and we have more knowledge and we would
do it slightly different and in a better
way that would sort of hook into curl in
a more futurep proof and less hacky way.
>> Yeah, I guess it's not a standard back
end that you're doing a protocol for. So
that sort of journey from the core of
lib curl to calling the backend hooks or
however you do it would have been
completely different and brand new.
>> Exactly. Because we learned a lot from
doing this and now we know more.
>> Yeah. So it's not a failure. It's just a
learning process.
>> Yes. Absolutely.
>> Okay. That brings us nicely on to
actually adding Rust. So having done
this myself, I have a bit of an idea,
but I just want to paint a picture of
what it was like before you even did
this. So normally when you configure
it's an auto toolsbased project. So
that's your configure make test. Is that
correct?
>> Yeah, pretty much.
>> And you have a CMake option as well, do
you?
>> Yes. Yeah, it's pretty much on par. So
you can select whichever version.
>> Yeah. So you're doing the configuration
part, running your configure script. So
we'll stick with auto tools. You might
do d-help and see how you build things,
what options you doing. And at that
point 2020, there was nothing in the
configure AC script that lets you detect
what's there, what's built. Nothing to
say build this or that. That's correct.
Yeah,
>> exactly.
>> Cool. So then there is no variable set
to then act on to say right use this
code instead of that code or compile
this code or that back end or check Rust
is installed or all the Rust ecosystem
is available. Correct.
>> Exactly.
>> Yeah. So really ground zero.
>> Yes. So how did you start this process
and can you give us an example of what
that look time period what bits you
tackle first
>> if you can remember
>> whenever I want to start to support
something new like this I typically just
I start with making sure that we can
detect it with configure so then I add
my configure rules first so that you
could add the d-with hyper and provide
the installation path pretty much like
whatever since we can support again you
can build with different backends. So
the same way you would decide other
backends with the configure line, you
would decide this back end. So you would
specify I want to use hyper. Hyper is
installed here and then I would provide
the proper configure magic so that it
would detect that hyper actually exists.
It is the proper version and then I made
sure that you would build with it.
That's the easy part, right? That just
making sure that the library is there
and can be used.
>> So how would you do that with Rust?
Would you need to create a little rush
program and then add the hyper module or
>> No, pretty much since we need the FFI
version or a it wasn't even the
generated FFI. It was some glue library
that Sean created first. So pretty much
I don't actually interface the hyper
library directly. I interface the little
glue library or wrapper library called
something else. And that's the library I
check for because that's the library
written with a C interface. And so I
just pretty much make sure that I can
find that library, link with that
library, and I can find a symbol in
there and I can link with it that I deem
it suitable and working.
>> Yeah, that's what I've done in my
project. And just I'll explain how I
understand it. And I think that's how
you've done it. So when you build a Rust
project, you tell the cargo or the Rust
ecosystem to build that as either a
static or shared library. It's not going
to be a binary and then install that
somewhere. And that's what you're trying
to detect, isn't it? and then saying
this function should be available
through that library
>> and then yeah that means it's installed
>> and then I make it just a set of define
for that and then in the build I can
just use an if defaf if this is
available use this code and if it's not
available use the other code yeah cool
that's how I understand it and hopefully
the listeners get that so yeah I mean
rust can be built into a library and
offer a foreign function interface for C
code I fi and that's what you're doing
>> yeah and then it was just a matter you
know, splitting up the code in a
suitable way. Sort of what can hyper
provide and make sure that I would
abstract it in a way so that I would
either use the native code or the hyper
library to do things. Setting up a
request, adding headers, parsing
headers, all that stuff you do with
HTTP, which actually is quite a lot.
>> And did you as far as the core was
concerned, it's just a C library you're
using. You didn't have to think about
how Rust did something or
>> Exactly. That's kind of the beauty of
it. I didn't have to think about it as
Rust at all. I just have an API and
that's just an API I get to use and it
doesn't matter how it's powered, right?
Which language is written in or
anything. I just have an API to use and
call.
>> It could have been any language really,
but we wanted RS because of the
>> Exactly. It doesn't or it didn't matter
to me, right? Whatever language it is
written in, it doesn't matter. I have an
API which with a documented behavior and
expected outcome and an input and
everything. So I would just use that.
And of course one of the challenges for
us then me and Sean from the hyper side
is that this was early days then for the
FFI things and me using hyper from a C
program. So most of this stuff didn't
actually exist. It wasn't really
documented. So we had to have a lot of
interactions for me to understand how to
use it. And one of the challenges
actually in general when it comes to
using Rust from C all these FFI things
is that most of the documentation even
though Rust provides this as a sort of a
fairly convenient way to generate code
so that you can use it from C is that
most of the documentation written for
these Rust libraries. They're written
for Rust consumers right users quite
naturally. But it makes it complicated
when you're not using the Rust API.
you're using this FFI API from C because
then you end up in a weird middle land.
You have to read a Rust documentation,
but it's not that way. It's actually
exposed to me because I'm using the C
API.
>> Yeah. Normally the sort of standard way
to do this is you create a Rust create
and it's got a suffix of - CIS. So Sys,
that's the bit that links to the C
library. And then you've got a nice Rust
idomatic crate that links to this SIS
thing. So you're hiding all the C stuff.
>> Exactly. But the documentation
>> Yeah. The way you do it is you've got to
generate the library and then all the
Rust doc things are documenting the
symbols and the function calls and the
return types cuz it's strongly typed on
the Rust side. And I don't think that
has an automate way to do it. Maybe
through buying gen and lipsy that offer
those things the other way. You said
that Sean So Hyper was just Rust, wasn't
it? It just was a library for Rust. It
didn't have anything built to generate
the C build.
>> No, but it was already in their plans.
So I really didn't sort of push for
anything they hadn't already intended to
do or it was just that they hadn't done
it yet. So I was pretty much the first
user of it. So did you have to work
together to create function names that
would be available through the library
version of hyper the C library version
that you would call or
>> yes because since it didn't exist so
they pretty much had to go through it
one by one and make sure that I could
access it from C and provide the
documentation for the C angle which is
an interesting challenge right and I
think that was one of the bigger
challenges in general when it comes to
doing this is as in this middle land
when there has to the C library or C
interface to access from the C code that
would then reach into the Rust code. It
means that you have to have someone that
is actually interested and knowledgeable
in both languages in that middle land to
understand it and be interested enough
to work with it and write the
documentation and provide the
functionality necessary for this to
actually work.
>> Yeah, because it's like it's double the
work, isn't it? cuz you've got to design
the rust function. Then you've got to
say on that rust function the standard
way we do it in curl I'm just guessing
here you've got to return a x success or
an exit failure or a pointer to an error
code or both you know saying right if
it's a nonzero return then you know
what's that so there's loads of things
to think once you've actually written
well how is it called and how are we
going to provide
>> yep
>> what curl needs and you lose a lot of
rust's main features you know the rich
error codes you can get and all those
types of things cuz you're squashing it
down to a one or a zero or a pointer.
>> Yeah, exactly. So, it has to be sort of
translated into the C world somehow.
>> And we've already said this was opt in.
Can you recall what issues you
immediately saw as Sean was working on
this interface layer or
>> Well, I think one of the primary first
things that we struggled with was the
inherent as sync nature at least that
hyper is written in. So that it made the
API quite unorthodox when it comes to
how normally C interfaces work because
they have a completely different
approach to how things work internally
and how they were exposed. So it was a
steep learning curve for me to
understand how to actually even use the
API. But that was more of a just getting
to know how things actually work. I
guess that just comes with the territory
when you have to use a library that is
fairly rich in features and you have to
integrate it. One of the biggest
challenges for me in general when doing
this is that we have a pretty extensive
test suite in curl and it's getting you
know increasingly more and more tests
over time. One of the things we do in
the test suite is that when we for
example verify HTTP HTTP1 when we do a
request with curl we verify that the
outgoing request is exactly as expected
you know every bite in the request has a
specific uh value it's supposed to be
right so a outgoing request we know that
if it's 120 bytes we know we can compare
it all those 120 bytes should be exactly
like this and the same way when we get a
response from the server the server
sends back a response That might be I
don't know how many bytes but all those
bytes should match exactly when we
download it exactly as the server sent
it or as the as curl saved it. That
actually introduced quite a lot of
interesting challenges because hyper has
a different approach to how they expose
HTTP details. So suddenly it was not at
all that as easy to do the test cases
the way we had done it for decades
because hyperexposed it differently. So
was already there was a challenge to
make sure that how do we verify that a
transfer done with the native code is
identical to a transfer done with hyper.
>> Yeah. So you haven't got that safety net
to fall back on to just if that test
fails, you know, you've not done
something right, you've actually got to
change the contract between
>> Yeah. So part of our first sort of steps
into making sure that this would work,
it was that we had to ask Sean to do
several different changes to Hyper so
that it would provide data in a more
curl like way so that we could actually
use it in the test suite and make sure
that the requests were not completely
identical but almost identical.
identical enough so that we could
actually tweak the test suite a little
bit so that we could run tests and make
sure that they actually work exactly the
same.
>> So to interface the C to the async hyper
which I'm not sure if you if it used
Tokyo or
>> it does I think
>> so is that a ton of callbacks you have
to do and wait for the reply or
>> No, I think they hide the call backs. So
they do the call backs. It means that
you do a lot of things but you don't get
to answer. I mean you sort of start an
operation but you don't get the answer
to the operation now. It just you know
returns okay but it hasn't actually
performed it yet. So you have to call it
again later to know if it went okay or
not in a way that was you know when you
introduce like for example like in my
case when I want to have an alternative
way to do HTTP I have the native way and
the Rust way to do it. it just
introduces some fun challenges when one
of the backends have a completely
different way of thinking about these
things than the other. So it made it
slightly complicated to make you know
selecting the two different forks of the
road and make sure that nothing else in
curl would see that or suffer from that
or misbehave because of the different
which of the different backends you
would use. So it was just a challenge
really.
>> Yeah. Imagine you've got a sort of AI or
API to add a new backend curl. So if I
was coming along and I'd created a brand
new protocol and I wanted curl to do it,
I know there would be documentation of
how I hook that into your configure and
build process, but that wasn't there for
this Rust version Hyper because you
hadn't done it before. So
>> yeah, exactly. You've got two moving
parts to try and line up and work and a
whole new sort of frontier to try and
pull things out of lip curl that you
hadn't done before as well. Okay. So,
what advice would you or could you give
others with regards to this build
process? Actually, the way you've
explained it, it's just another C
library.
>> Yes, I think that's a pretty neat way to
do it. So I think that's straightforward
and from a C point of view, from our
project's point of view, it was really
convenient and really working well. So
technically there's no problem. There's
nothing really that I think that should
or need to be changed when it comes to
that. I think the biggest problem and
come back to it because I already
mentioned it and I see the same problem
actually with the other Rust provided
backends is that again you end up in a
weird land where the documentation is
often fairly good for these Rust
libraries but they don't since I don't
interface the Rust API I end up in a
weird land where I don't actually have a
documentation for how my the API
interface I use isn't actually
documented. So I have to do a lot of
guessing or reading code or both or
guessing how it actually works because
the translation from Rust to C is not
always straightforward and it's not even
I mean I can't even guess at some points
because it it matters. It depends on how
you actually do that FFI translation
pretty much. So that's a sort of a
common pattern I see.
>> Could you give us an example of that?
Say we've got a function that does
something and returns something. that
function interface is documented, but
what problem?
>> Well, typically it's only documented.
The Rust version of it is documented.
Sure. So, there's a a it's a fairly
elaborate description of how it works
when used in Rust, but I don't use it in
Rust. I don't even understand what the
documentation says about the types and
how they they work and everything or
even the return code because that's not
exactly what I I don't pass in those
arguments. I don't get the same return
code. So I usually get a more of a
tweaked or twisted version of that API,
but I need the details in that
particular flavor because I use the C
API, not the Rust API.
>> Yeah, I see. When I've been doing some
functions, it's I've only written them
because a C program is going to be
calling them. So I've changed the, you
know, the signature of that function and
what it returns. But I guess if you've
got like a really
>> I think sometimes it's more of a case
that sort of as a C user in this sort of
situation. I'm the oddball here. I'm the
niche case. So of course people are
sacrificing spending spare time and
offering their time on this and energy.
They of course focus on getting things
working primarily for the Rust users. So
that's why the Rust documentation is is
the priority. And I don't argue with
that because it makes sense. But
sometimes that makes it harder to use it
from C because this documentation is
often
>> yeah the types and the structures and
the R side when they tell Rush to
represent that as C you just have to
kind of see what comes out don't you?
>> Yeah. And then it comes back to this to
do this really well you probably need to
understand quite a lot of Rust and C at
the same time and that's a special
intersection of people.
>> Excellent. So I'm going to move us on to
our what you call autopsy for one of a
better word. What went wrong? You know
the analysis here. So first question,
was this the right part of curl to use
rust in? Yes, I think it could have been
the right part to use rust in. I don't
think it was actually the part of curl
that was the problem because I think as
I said before, I think we can pretty
much introduce backends for more or less
anything in curl like this if we just
spend time and energy and do it
correctly. So I don't think it was the
part of curl that was the problem. I
think the primary thing that made us
eventually pull it out again is that we
didn't really find users that wanted it.
>> Yeah.
>> So we have this I kind of like the the
sort of the survival of the fittest
approach by offering different backends
for different solutions so that users
would pick whatever they want and go
with that. You know, we offer bunch of
different TLS library solutions, for
example, and users can pick whatever
they want and build curl and and use
that and we can over time detect that
wait a minute, these different ones are
never used. We don't have to support
them anymore. We can remove them. So,
pretty much letting users decide what we
should have and what's used and what's
best and what they want. It was quite
notable quite early on and through the
entire project that we had a hard time
to get anyone to actually even just try
out the hyper backend. So we had a
pretty much no one used it and by not
having users we also had very few
contributors you know helping out
improving the back end so that very few
people actually engaged and helped us
out. So
>> how do you figure out if a back end's
being used or is popular or not?
basically just by asking people. So we
have annual user surveys and usually you
know asking on the mailing list people
are frequent users are you using it or
sometimes you could just notice you know
by when we have had a serious bug for a
while and we fix it and no one has told
us about it. That's a sort of a pretty
big clue that no one actually used it.
We also marked it as experimental which
also of course is a blocker for people
to use it in production because we never
actually got it completely 100% the same
as the native. So we kept having I think
like 3 4% of the test cases disabled
because we had when you enabled hyper
because we never got those test cases
working exactly the same.
>> Yeah, I suppose you could argue if it
was marked as stable and then it became
the default option then you'd get bug
reports and people would opt in would
help out but if you didn't get there you
didn't get there.
>> Exactly. Yeah. Of course that's sort of
that was one obstacle certainly a major
one. And were the other Rust options,
the TLS stuff, was that there before you
started this project? So you had some
experience or was that done after?
>> The key one for HP3 that was started
before the Russell's one started I think
pretty much while I was doing this.
>> So that's Rust TLS, isn't it?
>> Rust TLS. We have a much better
understanding of TLS in curl and it
makes it's we have much better
infrastructure and setup for TLS
backends in curl. So I think that was so
that's a smoother ride and a better fit
into curl and also I think TLS is a
better abstraction layer I think maybe
than HTTP sort of quote unquote because
what the internal API or how to abstract
HTTP away it's certainly far from clear
and uh obvious how to do it and one of
the challenges we face many times I
already sort of alluded a little bit to
the that hyper and curl has a little bit
of different we have different sort of
approaches how we approach HP which made
it for example when getting the headers
from hyper it would get them in a more
or less random order while curl always
returns them in the order they were sent
over the wire which of course if I don't
have the same order I can't compare them
correctly as I do in my current test
suite so that's one thing for example
and other things like hyper has
certainly other limits restrictions
requirements on the HTTP layer than curl
which also introduced funny friction and
differences when you built one way or
the other way because they would behave
differently depending on just policies
or religion or taste.
>> The existing Rust things that you're
using were again just C libraries but in
a wellestablished landscape because you
had other backends already.
>> Yes. And this just this compacted it.
And there must have been a point or was
there a point when you thought, hold on,
we're having to make so many changes to
Hyper to get this to work. Did you ever
have a conversation about, well, let's
just do this from scratch because you
tried it out or was that just not a
thing?
>> I think that also because I'm not
qualified. I'm not skilled enough in
Rust myself to do that. So, I wouldn't
do it and therefore I wouldn't dream of
demanding it from someone else either.
So it was pretty much hyper or not at
all right now at least sort of because
now we had this hyper solution. This is
what we struggle to get working and I
think we got it pretty far as well. So I
mean we were at 90 I don't know 97% of
test case coverage. So I think we were
pretty well on our way to get it to work
but then it flatlined and no one worked
on it for a while. just sat at that
state and we didn't seem to have anyone
really interested in pushing it forward.
And when it was pretty much at that
state, we decided that wait a minute, if
if this is where we are, no one is
pushing for it and no one is really
asking for it either. And all of these
different caveats and we need to do
these different maybe not clutchy, but
maybe some sometimes a little bit of
uncomfortable or quirky solutions
internally. And still we're only at this
point. So maybe that's what we should
call a sort of a end of the road for
this adventure and say that we didn't
actually manage to do this in a proper
way.
>> Um that brings me nicely on to what
benefits did you gain from the attempt
which to me sound like a lot you know a
lot of things that you've learned.
>> I think we learned a lot. I think
actually Hyper also learned a lot. I
think they improved as well as we did.
So even though when we sort of split off
and we're no longer using hyper I think
we improved curl in several ways we made
the HTTP handling more rigid and and
stringent to match up with hyper really
and we did a lot of cleaning up
internally to be able to do this backend
separation and that helped us internally
to just do HTTP in a cleaner way and
then also this lesson that we learned
that we how we should do this the next
time pretty And this entire hyper
journey also coincided with other
refactors we've done in curl. And I
think the hyper lesson also helped us
make decisions and and learn from that
and use that when we refactored the
internals in curl. So that we sort of
have in the back of our minds we now
have this idea that when or maybe if we
do this again now we have these
different tools and and setups that will
help us do this better the next time.
Did any of the changes that you made to
to bring in Hyper, did they remain or
did you just rip them all out when you
removed Hyper?
>> A lot of the improvements we did to HTTP
in general and and the separation of
HTTP from other there were some cases of
pretty much of um I don't know how to
sort of explain it but you know that we
have sort of infected other code parts
with HTTP specific knowledge that we had
to make sure that they were not in the
generic parts they had to be in the HTTP
parts. So we did a lot of cleanups like
that that have certainly remained and
just been emphasized and improved over
time. So I would say that quite a lot of
the HTTP related the protocol related
parts they have remained. What we pretty
much ripped out was the entire attempt
to have this flexible backend approach
where we go either or way because we
don't have that anymore. So we don't
have to provide it. So that part we
ripped out.
>> That makes sense. In your blog post, you
said, so I'm just going to quote this
bit. 95% of the work is the easy part.
Can you explain the other sentence that
says the final few% would however turn
out to be frictional enough to now
eventually make us admit defeat, give
up, and instead yank it all out again.
>> So what those last bits
>> I think pretty much because we made
everything. We have about 2,000 test
cases in total. I think about 800 of
them or something. a thousand are about
HTTP and I think we had we were down to
maybe 15 of them failing with Hyper and
getting those final 15 test cases to
work. Those were the ones that sort of
finally broke us because they require
that someone actually understand
hyper probably the C glue layer and curl
and the protocols involved and sometimes
more protocols involved because
sometimes they also involve actually in
these cases many times they involve HTTP
authentication mechanisms too like NLM
or digest or negotiate horrible things.
So you really need particular kind of
person with intimate knowledge of all
this and not only knowledge but you also
have one you need an interest and an
energy enough to actually dig into this
and work on this and we basically didn't
find those persons with that time and
energy. So they remained there and I
didn't see any easy outcome. I didn't
see anyone likely to show up to do this
work. So
>> those 15 tests, do you recall a couple
of them what they were and and why they
failed and
>> well why they failed? That's part of the
reason why if we knew exactly why they
failed, it would have been easier. But
that was part of the research that would
have been done. It's in the in the
interaction or the differences between
the hyper solution to do things to the
native solution to do things. And I
could also just add that hyper is not
doing everything. curl can do a lot more
HTTP than hyper can. So the HTTP back
end Hyper provides was not everything
HTTP. So there was still part of HTTP
that curl did natively. For example, all
those authentication mechanisms, there
was this interaction or middle where
curl would do set up things magically to
how to do HTTP and when it would use and
interact with Hyper to perform the HTTP
requests, but also it's not easy to
explain and I don't recall the details
right now, but there were mostly cases
like that and they would end up slightly
different than you know the requests or
the responses would be slightly
different depending on which solution
you would use And the entire challenge
there would be to figure out why and and
what to do to fix it.
>> I think I can imagine because I've done
similar in my C project bringing Rust
into it which is another reason why I
was interested. So I imagine that the
bits that curl still does that Hyper
doesn't or never will. You set those up.
You're giving your data. So you're
passing stuff that's being created is in
memory. you know, is all aligned or what
have you on on the curl C side of the
FFI boundary. You shove that across to
Rust. It has to then interpret and
understand all that bit correctly, do
its bit, make changes, and then pass
stuff back across the FFI boundary from
Rust to C and hope that bit doesn't get
messed up. And then you've got the
strict agreements of who's managing
memory, who's doing what, who's freeing
things, who's setting it up, and that
can get complicated very quickly.
>> Yes. So that type of interaction because
it was hyper is not a full 100%
replacement for what Carl is doing.
>> Exactly. And by the fact that it is
doing things differently. So it was also
that nature. So it was just you know
fairly complicated programming
challenge. I mean not impossible of
course but it was just challenging
enough that it turned out to be an
obstacle that no one really worked on.
And when no one has had worked on it for
long enough, I took it as a sign that
it's probably not something people want
to work on either. And no one showed up
interested in doing it either. Well,
people did work on it that helped us out
and and we got this far thanks not only
to me of course or to Sean, but actually
also to a whole bunch of other
contributors who helped out. So there
were people around. I mean, you hold
very very high standards obviously
because it's your baby. But you could
argue that it's a success. You know, you
got that far and you had 15 tests left
to solve. I mean, that's a pretty big
win, wasn't it? Really?
>> I mean, I think we proved that it
actually could work. It proved that the
idea was solid and the implementation
wasn't perfect, but it worked. So, I
think in that aspect, it was a win, but
then in the end, we didn't go all the
way. And I was also the fact that we
didn't really have anyone asking for
this or using this or pushing for this,
you know, there was no demand from the
user side either. That was also sort of
a pretty big factor because there was
no, you know, big gain in the end of all
this struggle either.
>> Yeah. It's a feature build that if no
one's asking for it, you know, it's a
feature really, isn't it?
>> Right. And so in the end it felt like
yeah there's final friction here that we
could maybe surpass and go through if we
really made an effort but there was no
one asking us to do that and the big
trophy in the end was missing.
>> Did you have a timeline by the sponsors
of this feature? I forget the acronym.
Did they say you had a year five years
or just how did that work?
>> No it wasn't really like that. They were
much more flexible in ISRG. So they were
really great with this. So they were
fully on board with this and I had a
full communication with them during over
the years really and even when we came
to this conclusion it wasn't really a
conclusion first. It was more like a
thought that maybe we should just
conclude defeat here and give up and rip
it out again. So I had conversation with
them all the time and they were very
good with this and they understand it
completely. they struggle quite a lot
too to find people to actually you know
pick up the ball and continue this work
and in the end I think we all concluded
that this is the right decision for now
I mean we haven't shut the door for this
idea or this effort or this concept for
the future anyway so who knows maybe we
will come back to this idea and restart
it in the future
>> yeah there might be some trigger that
comes out and it's just a a no-brainer
to pick it up that's the beauty of
source control you've got all the
history there. I think I've asked this
already or we've touched it. What can
others learn from this?
>> The general lesson is basically that
it's it is a fair approach to replace
C++ code in a larger project. So you can
I kind of always like that approach with
Rust already back from the days I worked
with Firefox that it's it's a convenient
and decent way to replace components
sort of component by component wise
instead of having to rewrite everything
into Rust in one single blow. You can
instead do it component by component. I
and I still think that's a good way to
do it and I think we proved that it
works to do it that way. other things I
I think it's harder because then you get
into the weeds of exactly how the API
works and how to actually replace a
component in a software and that depends
on the particular software I think more
than anything else. I think we've
covered my last question which would be
why didn't others step forward to help
and you explained that the knowledge
domain here is like four different
things you know there's the rust way to
do it there's the C interface there's
the particular bit you're replacing on
curl and then the protocols or the specs
involved with that whether it's
authentication or you know HTTP version
4 when that comes out etc. Yeah, and I
think just the general lack of a
perceived upside of of using this. I
don't think most people think curl's
native solution is bad or insecure and
anything. So people wouldn't sort of
dream of switching over to this new one
anyway. So we're stuck in the land where
people using curl, they they're pretty
satisfied with the existing solution.
People using Hyper, they're mostly Rust
users. They're they're in Rust land.
They're using Hyper already. They don't
use curl anyway. So we ended up in this
middle land with no demand.
>> Yeah. I suppose if this was the hot spot
of memory related security issues or
what have you, you'd either take the
decision to address them and see and fix
them like you're constantly doing
refactoring to make improvements or you
bring rust in to do it. But without the
sort of raw data to say you know given x
amount of effort you'll get y amount of
return it's hard to really quantify it.
Yeah, we can also come back to the fact
that my plan is not to remove the native
C alternative anyway because I think the
portability of curl and and curl's
prevalence on everything everywhere is
partly due to it being massively
portable and it is this portable because
it is written in C. So even if we had
kept the hyper back end, we would have
kept the native one as well. So we still
need to work on the native one even if
we would have provided a rust one. And
are you aware of any C projects that you
reviewed or listeners could review that
do what you already do with Rust and
parts for example or
>> one sort of obvious sibling project to
this is the I think it's called mod TLS
thing in the Apache web server where I
know Stefan Iing has written a
replacement for the open SSL using
module for Apache that is then using
Rust TLS instead when you run the Apache
web server which is pretty much the same
take right by replacing well slightly
different take but it's the same spirit
that they replace a C library with a
Rust library in order to do more memory
safe operations. Yeah, I'll put that in
the show notes and get that link off
you. I think we had a quick chat before
we started recording about Rust TLS and
how it can use a C library underneath of
a TLS implementation as well. So you've
always got some CLS code somewhere
depending on
>> Yes. Yeah. And that's sometimes a bit
ironic, right? When talking about using
Rust for memory safety and then you end
up using the C version somewhere in
there anyway.
>> Exactly. Okay. I think I'm going to wrap
us up now. I'm really glad glad we did
this show and hope it helps others
understand how they can add Rust into
their C project, make it success. And as
we discussed, I it wasn't a failure. It
was just, you know, a feature that
didn't have enough demand and benefit
and got very very complicated at the
end. Was there anything we missed that
you'd like to mention that was a
particular highlight or challenge that
you solved or just anything in general?
>> No, I think we covered most of what I
wanted to say. Maybe just to reiterate
that Sean and the Hyper project, they
were really great and they helped out a
lot. there's really no blame on their
side because certainly not because of
lack of energy or lack of commitment
from their side. It was basically just
well everything we talk about.
>> So how can people get in touch if they
like to ask you particular things or you
know maybe investigate some of these
tests? Is this now gone until you get
some capacity to do it again or drive
appetite?
>> All this is now gone from git. So if you
want to bring back you have to bring
back an old version and build from
source and and try it out. I mean, you
could do it if you're really interested
into what kind of weird
problems you can run into when you do
this, but otherwise it's not that
fruitful. I think now we're heading
forward instead. So, we're looking into
of course improving curl in every
possible aspect and going forward. And
if anyone ever think doing it again is
would be a great idea, then we would of
course consider getting this back onto
the drawing table and do it better next
time. But everything that is about curl
is of course on curl.s SC on and just
hit us up
>> and your blog as well. Yeah.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> Yeah. I wonder if anything will come
along like a hyper version two that has
particular thing. But I guess with the
author of Hyper and you know the expert
you are, you would have solved it if it
was there. Cool. Okay, Daniel, thank you
for coming on the show. It's been a real
pleasure. This is Gavin Henry for
Software Engineering Radio. Thank you
for listening.
>> Bye.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
ITLE e software magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE radio
is licensed under creative comments
license 2.5.
Thanks for listening.